A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential papers, Vice Presidential Confirmation, Series 4 FA1202
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller Vice Presidential papers, Vice Presidential Confirmation, Series 4
1965-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
United States. Office of the Vice President
Herter, Susan C.
FA1202
4.63 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes 5 legal document boxes
Scope and Contents
This small series contains two subseries from different time periods in Nelson Rockefeller's political career. The first one documents the confirmation hearings held in the autumn of 1974 by the U.S. Senate and House of Representatives to vet Mr. Rockefeller for the role of Vice President. The second one is a selection of records from his tenure as Vice President, most likely from the office of staff member Susan Herter.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
This series has two subseries: the Vice Presidential Confirmation Hearings and the Vice Presidency. The first subseries is arranged quasi-chronologically over the 4 months of the confirmation hearings in 1974. The second subseries starts with staff correspondence and is followed by chronological trip files. The last box is mostly files on Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller's official activities as the spouse of the Vice President.
Vice-Presidents -- United States
- Vice Presidential Confirmation, 1965-1974; 1
  Scope and Contents
  On August 20, 1974, recently sworn-in President Gerald R. Ford formally nominated Nelson A. Rockefeller to be Vice President of the United States, in accordance with the Twenty-Fifth Amendment of the Constitution. Over the course of the next four months, the U.S. Senate and the House of Representatives held separate, extensive confirmation hearings on Governor Rockefeller's nomination.
  During the hearings, members of the Senate Committee requested substantial documentation related to Governor Rockefeller's financial and professional activities from the previous decade. This subseries contains documentation of the efforts to respond to those requests, mostly from the office of his press secretary, Hugh Morrow. Transcripts, position statements, and briefing books are other types of materials in this subseries.
  On December 19, 1974, Nelson Rockefeller was sworn in as the forty-first U.S. Vice President, having successfully navigated the confirmation process. He served until January 20, 1977.
  - Senate Hearing Index, 1974 September 23-26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Index to transcripts of hearings by the U.S. Senate Committe on Rules and Administration
  - Senate Hearing Transcripts, 1974 September 23-26 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - Prepared Statements of Senate Committee Witnesses, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Senate Committee Hearing Inserts and Digests, 1974 September 23-25 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Digests are 1) chronological and 2) by committee member who asked the questions.
  - Issue Summaries and Statements, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Information Requests and Compliance Letters, 1974 September-October (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Summaries of State and Federal Issues, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Information Request on Attica Prison Events, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    These records address events of an uprising at Attica Prison in western New York in September 1971, during Nelson A. Rockefeller's tenure as Governor.
  - President Gerald Ford's Positions on National Issues, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Digest of several domestic issues and statements on the President's history regarding each.
  - Senate Hearings Related Material, 1974 September (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Background Information on Senate Rules Committee Members, 1974 September (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Compiled by Governor Rockefeller's staff to provide an idea of the type of questions each member of the Senate committee typically asks, including what they asked of President Ford during his confirmation hearings.
  - Briefing Book on Foreign Policy Issues, 1974 September-October (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
    Prepared by the National Security Council for the Vice President-Designate. It is unclear if there are differences between the two books from September. The smaller briefing from October contains updates to specific sections.
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Press Conferences, 1974 August 23-September 3 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Index to Confirmation Hearings, 1974 November (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    Senate Hearings index for November 13-15 and House of Representatives Hearings index for November 21-22.
  - Statement to the Senate Rules Committee, 1974 September 23 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Transcript of Nelson Rockefeller's formal opening statement to the U.S. Senate Commmittee on Rules and Administration during the vice presidential confirmation hearings.
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Binder on Statement to Senate Rules Committee, 1974 September (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Rockefeller's preparation binder on his statement before the Senate Committee
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Handwritten Drafts and Notes for Statement, 1974 September (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
  - Statement to House Judiciary Committee, 1974 November 21 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Press release of Nelson Rockefeller's full statement at the opening of the confirmation hearings held by House of Representatives Judiciary Committee.
  - Unsorted Hearings Material, 1974 September-December (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Incoming Gubernatorial Correspondence, 1965-1973 (Box 5, Folder 30-36)
    Background material from Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as Governor of New York. Likely from Alton Marshall's office during his service as Secretary to the Governor.
  - Laurance S. Rockefeller Statement to the Press, 1974 October 10 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Press Statements and Advisories, 1974 October (Box 6, Folder 38-43)
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Handwritten Notes and Drafts for Statements, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Hugh Morrow's Statements to the Press, 1974 October (Box 6, Folder 45)
    Hugh Morrow served as Nelson Rockefeller's director of communications.
  - Summary of NAR Gifts, 1974 October (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Summary of NAR Gifts to Rockefeller Brothers Fund, 1974 October (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Correspondence with Senator Cannon and Representative Rodino, 1974 September-October (Box 6, Folder 48, 51-52)
    Letters with the Chairs of the Congressional committees leading the Vice Presidential hearings.
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Statement on L. Judson Morhouse, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - List of Countries Visited by Nelson Rockefeller, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Hugh Morrow's Files on NAR's Confirmation Process, 1974 October-November (Box 6, Folder 53-54)
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Gifts to William Ronan, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    William Ronan served as Secretary to the Governor during Nelson Rockefeller's first 3 terms in office.
  - Summary of Loans Given by Nelson Rockefeller, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence with Representative Mezvinsky, 1974 October (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Nelson Rockefeller's Press Release and Drafts on Arthur Goldberg, 1974 October (Box 6, Folder 58-59)
    Arthur Goldberg was the Democratic candidate for New York Governor in 1970, having previously served as a Justice on the U.S. Supreme Court.
  - White House Contacts, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - John Lockwood's Confirmation Correspondence, 1974 September (Box 6, Folder 61)
    John Lockwood served as counsel to the Rockefeller Family Office and Rockefeller Center Inc.
  - George Hinman's Confirmation Correspondence, 1974 August- October (Box 6, Folder 62)
    George Hinman served as an executive assistant to Governor Rockefeller and was one of his chief political advisors.
  - Correspondence with John Mitchell and John Ehrlichman, 1970s (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Unsorted Confirmation Hearings Material, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Drafts of Nelson Rockefeller's Statement to the Senate Committee, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 71-72)
  - Drafts of Descriptions of Loans Made by Nelson Rockefeller, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 73-74)
    Complied and submitted in response to questions from the Senate Committee
  - Letter of Appreciation from Nelson Rockefeller, 1974 December (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Planning File for Vice President-Designate, 1974 December (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Vice President's Residence (Admiral's House) (Box 8, Folder 77-78)
    Background information on the establishment of the residence for the Vice President at the former Admiral's House on the grounds of the U.S. Naval Observatory.
- Vice Presidency, 1974 December-1977 January; 2
  This small subseries dates from Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as U.S. Vice President. It is a partial run of staff correspondence files, background reports, and trip files, possibly maintained by staff member Susan Herter. There is also a handful of folders on scheduling and logistics for Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller's offical events in 1975.
  - Staff Correspondence from Susan Herter's Office, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 79-88)
    Correspondence files maintained by Susan Herter with several Vice Presidential staff members: Richard Allison; Robert Armao; Spofford Canfield; Joseph Canzeri; Howard Dixon; Richard Dunham; Thaddeus Garrett; Roger W. Hooker, Jr.; and Capt. Jonathan Howe.
  - Monthly Correspondence Statistics, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    Monthly information provided to Susan Herter on correspondence statistics for the Vice President's Office
  - Colorado Springs, CO, Trip, 1976 June (Box 10, Folder 90)
    The Vice President gave the commencement address to the U.S. Air Force Academy's graduating class of 1976.
  - Republican National Convention Trip, Kansas City, MO, 1976-08 (Box 10, Folder 91)
  - Domestic Trips, 1976 April- October (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - World Trip, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    The Vice President visited multiple nations in conjunction with celebrations in those countries of the U.S. Bicentennial.
  - Cables Related to World Trip, 1976 January-March (Box 10, Folder 94)
  - Italy and Germany Trip, 1976 April-May (Box 10, Folder 95)
  - Spain Trip, 1976 November (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - Speech at National Press Club, 1976 October 25 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - McKay Commission Information, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - Review of Domestic and International Issues, 1976 December (Box 11, Folder 99-101)
  - Christmas Card Information, 1976 (Box 11, Folder 102)
  - Transition Planning at End of Vice President's Term, 1976 November (Box 11, Folder 103)
  - Vice President's Residence (Admiral's House), 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 104)
    Mostly lists of the personal furnishings and artwork that Nelson Rockefeller brought with him to the Vice President's residence.
  - Official Events Hosted or Attended by Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller, 1975 January-May (Box 11, Folder 105-111)
    Files on social events, maintained by Susan Herter.
  - Chronological Correspondence Files for Margaretta (Happy) Rockefeller, 1975 January-December (Box 11, Folder 112-114)
    Correspondence files maintained by Susan Herter